International Council of Women Records, 1888-1959
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
International Council of Women records
1888-1959
International Council of Women
MS 352
4 boxes (1.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
A small collection, including correspondence, minutes and committee reports; records of international conferences; constitutions; membership lists; and publications, including biographical information on ICW leaders. Topics include fine arts, health, education, housing, suffrage, laws, social welfare, trades and professions, The United Nations, and peace.
The International Council of Women (ICW), founded in 1888, was one of the first international women's organizations. The second international conference of the National Woman Suffrage Association, called by Susan B. Anthony, May Wright Sewall, and other suffragists, created the ICW. The aim of the conference was to form a National Council of Women in each self-governing country of the world. The councils would bring women from many countries together to work for women, not only in the cause of suffrage, but on many fronts. The United States National Council formed immediately, but progress elsewhere was slow. By 1893, Canada had formed a national body. In Great Britain the National Union of Women Workers federated with the National Council of Women in 1898 and later changed its name to the International Council of Women. By 1938 the number of councils affiliated with the ICW, which had developed into one of the best known and most consulted of women's international organizations, had risen to thirty-six.
In the early years of its existence, the ICW promoted National Councils and gained acceptance in the international community, but it's primary activity was planning the regular congresses. The ICW, regarded by members of other women's groups as the most conservative of women's international organizations, took pride in it's reputation, viewing it as a consequence of maintaining a broad program. It's early refusal to take a position on suffrage contributed to the formation of more radical organizations, such as the International Alliance of Women. In 1899, the Council began to take on more substantive issues, forming an International Standing Committee on Peace and International Arbitration. Other standing committees were soon established, and through them, the ICW became involved in issues from suffrage to health.
World War II caused great disorganization in the Council's work. Some national councils discontinued their work altogether; in others the leadership and organization were disrupted. In 1946, the ICW met in Philadelphia to re-focus its efforts and recover its former unity. The Conference issued a statement condemning war and all crimes against humanity, as well as demanding a more active role for women in the national and international arena.
Since its inception in 1888, the ICW's aims have been consistent-the unification of women's organizations for action to promote human rights, sexual equality, peace, and women's involvement in the international sphere. As of 2002, there are National Councils in seventy-five countries, and Regional Councils in America and Europe. The ICW continues to organize women globally, focusing on local education and health programs.
For further information about the ICW see: Worlds of Women: The Making of an International Women's Movement by Leila J. Rupp (Princeton University Press: Princeton, NJ, 1997).
The International Council of Women Records are by no means the complete body of records for this organization. They appear to be a more idiosyncratic collection, possibly donated by a member active in the 1950s and 1960s. They include correspondence, minutes and committee reports; records of international conferences; constitutions; membership lists; and publications, including biographical information on Lady Ishbel Aberdeen, Rachel Foster Avery, May Wright Sewall, Frances Willard, and other ICW leaders. The committee files include material regarding the ICW's activities in specific subject areas, such as fine arts, health, education, housing, suffrage, laws, social welfare, trades and professions, The United Nations, and peace. Correspondents include Vera Beggs and Alice M.Stetten.
This collection is organized into five series:
I. Organization and Administration
II. Committees
III. Conferences and Meetings
IV. Publications
V. National Councils
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The Records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
The provenance of the ICW Records is unknown. It appears that a member of the Council, possibly Grace Gallatin Seton, whose papers are also in the SSC, may have donated her own files.
Search Terms
International Council of Women--History--Sources; National Council of Women of the United States--History--Sources; Women--International cooperation--History--20th century--Sources; Women--Societies and clubs--United States--History--Sources; Women's rights--Congresses--History--Sources; Aberdeen, Ishbel, 1857-1939; Avery, Rachel Foster, 1858-; Eder, Jeanne--Correspondence; Beggs, Vera W. (Vera Wadsworth), d. 1968--Correspondence; Gilman, Charlotte Perkins, 1860-1935; Salomon, Alice, 1872-1948; Sewall, May Wright, 1844-1920; Stetten, Alice Mayer, 1887-1972.--Correspondence; Willard, Frances Elizabeth, 1839-1898
Additional Information
Bibliography
Rupp, Leila J. Worlds of Women: The Making of an International Women's Movement. (Princeton University Press: Princeton, NJ, 1997).
- SERIES I. ORGANIZATION AND ADMINISTRATION
  There is a small amount of material in this series, including constitutions and by-laws, histories and memorabilia, biographical material on Alice Salomon, correspondence, and miscellaneous material.
- SERIES II. COMMITTEES
  This series consists of general material relating to standing committees, as well as documents produced by individual committees covering subject areas such as arts and letters, cinema, education, housing, international relations and peace, social welfare, and trades and professions (arranged alphabetically by committee name). The bulk of the items were created in the 1950s and 60s.
- SERIES III. CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS
  This largest series contains records of ICW Conferences and meetings, arranged chronologically. There is one folder of material related to board meetings in the 1950s and 1960s.
- SERIES IV. PUBLICATIONS
  This series is a miscellaneous collection of various ICW published reports, newsletters and other periodicals, pamphlets, press releases, and newspaper clippings. As is the case in the other series, the bulk of the material was published in the 1950s and 1960s.
- SERIES V. NATIONAL COUNCILS
  This series is arranged alphabetically by country, contains small files on many of the National Councils, again primarily from the 1950s-60s, consisting primarily of constitutions, correspondence, reports, and lists.
- SERIES I. ORGANIZATION AND ADMINISTRATION
  - Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1936, 1953-54, 1962, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Histories and memorabilia, 1888-1963, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Archives, 1953-55 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Alice Salomon: biographical materials, 1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence
    - Dr. Jeanne Eder, 1950-53 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1950-59, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous lists, reports, and mailings, 1957-72, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- SERIES II. COMMITTEES
  - Standing committees, 1957-60 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Arts and Letters, 1950-61 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cinema, 1931, 1951, 1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Education, 1950-51, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Executive, 1951, 1963-64 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - F.A.O. [Food and Agriculture Organization of the U.N. ?], 1960? (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Finance, 1950, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Health, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Home Economics, 1950, 1961-62 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Housing, 1950, 1963, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - International Committee for the World Refugee Year, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - International Relations and Peace, 1947, 1960, 1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Laws and Suffrage, 1950-51, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Migration, 1951, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Moral Welfare, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Radio and Television, 1950-51, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Social Welfare, 1950-51, 1960, 1963-64 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Trades and Professions, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - United Nations, 1951, 1960-63 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Women in Community Development (ad hoc), 1966 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- SERIES III. CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS
  - First International Women's Conference, Washington, DC, 1888
    - General: speech by Isabella Beecher Hooker and The Birth of the I.C.W. 1938 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Report of the International Council of Women, 1888 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - International Council of Women, Berlin, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Quinquennial Meeting, Rome, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Meeting with the League of Nations, 10 Apr 1919 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Eighth Quinquennial Meeting, Vienna, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - International Congress of Women, Chicago, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Joint Conference of the International Council of Women and the International Council of Women in India, Calcutta, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - First Post-war Conference, Philadelphia, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Triennial meeting, Athens, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Triennial meeting, Helsinki, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Sixteenth Triennial meeting, Istanbul, 1960
    - Programs, correspondence, reports, and resolutions, 1959-60 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Nominations (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Seventeenth Triennial meeting, Washington, DC, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Eighteenth Triennial meeting, Tehran, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Nineteenth Plenary Conference, Bangkok, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Board meetings, 1950-62 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- SERIES IV. PUBLICATIONS
  - Biennial Report, 1925-27 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bulletin: 1947 issues and notes for 1952-53 issues (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Quarterly: First Quarter 1960 issue and correspondence, 1959-60 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Monthly News Sheet/Newsletter, 1956-70 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous: pamphlets by and about, brochures, press releases, and clippings, 1930-67, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- SERIES V. NATIONAL COUNCILS
  - Miscellaneous reports and lists, 1947-61, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Australia, 1953-66, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Bolivia, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Cameroon, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Canada, 1949-60 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Denmark, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - France, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Ghana, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Great Britain, 1960-61 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Greece, 1960-61 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Haiti, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - India, 1948, 1950, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Iran, 1966-67 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Italy, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Kenya, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Netherlands, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - New Zealand, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Nigeria, 1960-61, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Norway, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Peru, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Rhodesia, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - South Africa, 1960, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Sweden, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Turkey, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Uganda, 1960-61 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - United States, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Books on Shelf
  - National Council of the United States, Our Common Cause Civilization 1933
  - --------------------, Transactions of the National Council of Women of the United States, Assembled in Washington, D.C., February 22 to 25, 1891 1891